[snorts]
>> War ravaging the East since 1937 [music]
and Japan's invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history of the greatest of
all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the price of empire.
War itself demands On the day of his
third inauguration as president of the
United States, Franklin D. Roosevelt
scribbled a quite famous note to Winston
Churchill.
In it, he quoted the poet Longfellow.
Sail on, O ship of state. Sail on, O
union strong and great.
Humanity with all its fears, with all
the hope of future years,
is hanging breathless on thy fate.
As ever yours, Franklin D. Roosevelt.
In January 1941, when Roosevelt
scribbled the note,
Churchill's Britain stood alone against
the totalitarian dictators.
Before 1941 was half over,
the Soviet Union was locked in a titanic
struggle with Hitler's Germany.
Before the year was out, humanity, with
all the hope of future years,
would be hanging on the fate of
Roosevelt's great union,
compelled to join the struggle by what
he termed a date which will live
in infamy.
The night before the Japanese hit us, my
friend and I got into trouble in
Honolulu.
We were waiting for a taxi cab, and he
never did show up, so we jumped [music]
in one that
was vacant and took it for a ride.
And
they got us for malicious conversion,
whatever that be.
Japan did not declare war on the United
States.
Japan did not want to wage war against
the United States.
>> [music]
>> Japan knew that it could never win such
a war.
What Japan wanted was to nullify
American power for long enough to enable
it to grab such a strong bargaining
position that it would walk enriched
from peace talks.
That meant a preemptive [music] strike
designed to keep American power out of
the Japanese theater of operations.
[music]
Because of the wide ocean separating
that theater from the continental USA,
power meant naval power.
This was the reasoning that turned
Japanese [music] military planners
attention towards the closest
significant American base, the great
naval installation at Pearl Harbor in
Hawaii.
At the outbreak of the Second World War,
the American Army was rated 18th in the
world behind that of Czechoslovakia, a
country that had offered Hitler no
resistance.
>> [music]
>> But it had the most powerful navy in the
world.
If the Pacific [music] Fleet at anchor
in Pearl Harbor could be crippled, then
[music] Japan could carry out its
offensive and create the Greater East
Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere.
Lack of natural resources, particularly
oil, was the engine driving Japan's
thirst for expansion.
The sphere
>> [music]
>> was a propaganda conceit. The area was
known in Japan as the Southern Resources
Area.
Following the occupation of Indochina,
the USA had imposed an oil embargo which
denied Japan 90% of her oil imports. As
a result, the Japanese Navy calculated
it would run out of oil within a year.
Action now.
Tasked with launching the offensive,
Admiral Isoroku Yamamoto, commander of
the Combined Fleet, prophetically said,
"In the first 6 to 12 months of a war
with the United States and Britain, I
will run wild [music] and win victory
after victory.
After that, I have no expectation
[music] of success.
The fleet sailed on a sweeping northern
course hoping to avoid detection by
patrolling aircraft or ships.
Yamamoto sent the go signal.
Mount Niitaka on Taiwan was the highest
mountain in the Japanese Empire.
Niitaka yama nobore, the message said.
Climb Mount Niitaka.
With absolute surprise, 358
Japanese aircraft in two waves began
their [music] attack at 7:48 a.m. local
time on December the 7th, 1941.
The incoming aircraft [music] had been
picked up on radar, but the warning had
been ignored.
It was assumed that they were American
bombers arriving from California.
We were thinking about the Army Air
Force. They used to have maneuvers on
Sunday morning.
We said that they're kind of early this
morning.
Then pretty soon we saw
a bomb drop.
We said that this isn't the Army Air
Force, so sound general quarters and
and we went up to our battle stations
and
fired at planes coming over. It went on
for
a couple of hours.
They said me and my gunner got
credit for a plane and a half. How they
figure, I don't know.
We just stayed at battle stations.
And we saw the Arizona get hit.
Four out of every five men aboard the
Arizona were killed. 1,100 out of the
2,403
American fatalities on the day.
A lot of a lot of the guys uh
were caught in fires and jumped over the
side.
Some of them drowned, some of them
burned to death, some of them
But uh
I was one of the lucky ones in that
case, though.
Pearl Harbor's great oil storage
installation had not been attacked. Of
more lasting consequence, two of
America's aircraft carriers had been at
sea during the attack. And in Pearl's
shallow waters, [music] damaged ships
were grounded rather than sunk. Most
were quickly salvaged and repaired.
December 7th,
1941,
a date which will live
in infamy.
United States of America
was suddenly and deliberately attacked
by naval and air forces of the Empire of
Japan.
A board of inquiry held Rear Admiral
Kimmel, commander of the fleet, and
Lieutenant [music] General Short, army
commander, responsible.
Reduced in [music] rank, they were
compulsorily retired. A later
congressional committee found that
intelligence [music] reports available
in Washington had not been forwarded to
the two [music] men who were exonerated
and restored in rank. But that was not
until 1999,
by which time both men were dead.
The day after Pearl Harbor, December the
8th, Congress voted for war with Japan.
The motion carried in the Senate by 82
votes to none [music] and in the
representatives by 388 votes to one.
The dissenting [music] voice, that of
Jeannette Rankin of Montana, a pacifist
who was forced to hide from a mob after
the vote and who did not contest the
[music] next election.
America was at war. What that might mean
on the other side of the Atlantic was
not immediately clear.
Congress had voted for war with Japan.
Recruiting offices throughout America
were forced to remain open all night.
There was a skating rink at 68th Street,
the Boulevard. There was a plumbing
store there.
It was about 2:30 in the afternoon, a
loudspeaker come come on and it said,
"Everybody, we're closing, go home. The
Japanese just attacked Pearl Harbor."
I was hanging out on the corner like we
did in them days with my [music] gang of
friends and we heard that Pearl Harbor
was attacked. Nobody knew where Pearl
Harbor was. Never heard of it before.
I remembered very clearly cuz at the
time there was a football game going on
in Chicago.
When it came over the news,
it was amazing
the
the shock of everybody, number one,
but the The
thing was that the next day
hundreds
of boys left immediately to join the Red
Army. Our country is now at war, and I
feel that I can do more good in the Navy
than I can on the baseball field.
One of the war's most effective [music]
and colorful spies was Richard Sorge, a
Soviet agent working in the German
embassy in Tokyo.
Sorge had accurately warned of Operation
Barbarossa and been ignored. When he
warned Stalin of Pearl Harbor, he was
not ignored.
In October and November, Stalin,
realizing that Japan was not a threat
because of its commitment to war with
America, transferred 10 divisions, 1,000
tanks, and 1,000 aircraft from the
Siberian reserve to face Hitler.
Richard [music] Sorge continued to
provide intelligence to Moscow until his
capture, torture, and execution in 1944.
Operation Barbarossa had faltered and
failed in the mud of autumn and the snow
of winter.
Of the half million horses that the
German army had brought into the USSR,
[music]
half were dead before the spring of
1942.
It was in these bitter conditions that
the Red Army counterattacked.
The day before Pearl Harbor, Zhukov had
launched the West Front, the army
grouping south of the Kalinin Front
across the frozen Volga.
The next day, he launched his attack
south of Moscow.
What is
storm took up Russia?
And I said to
be really possible [music]
in Russia.
There will be pretty well done a lot.
>> On the 7th of December, the German
commander-in-chief, von Brauchitsch,
resigned following a heart attack.
Hitler refused to accept the
resignation.
In a very few days, he would [music]
change his mind and replace von
Brauchitsch with himself.
Soviet forces were outnumbered by their
enemy and poorer in every type of
equipment except for coats and boots.
The Germans, anticipating victory before
winter, had not equipped their army with
the means to survive Russia's deadly
cold. Their machines stopped working,
their antifreeze froze, and so did their
lubricants.
They had advanced with transport
scavenged from the conquered lands, so
one armored division, for example, had
employed more than 100 types of truck
and 37 types of motorbike. Such
inefficiency [music]
has given rise to the opinion that how
well the Germans fought masked how badly
they made war.
When Marshal Timoshenko's Southwest
Front began to move forward on December
13th, [music] von Brauchitsch,
consulting with von Bock in command of
Army Group Center, agreed [music] to a
withdrawal to a winter defensive
position about 145 km to the rear.
On the 14th, Hitler reacted
furiously.
He replaced von Bock. Over the next few
days, he replaced Guderian and accepted
von Brauchitsch's resignation.
On December the 20th, Joseph Goebbels
broadcast an appeal for winter clothes.
Soviet losses to December 1941 were 4
million troops, 8,000 aircraft, and
14,000 tanks. They had lost half their
iron and steel capacity and their
richest food-producing region.
How, from such a perilous position, the
Soviet Union was able to recover and
ultimately inflict a crushing defeat on
the invader is a question at the heart
of understanding the Second World War.
In early January, the Soviet assault was
renewed and when on January the 12th,
the commander of Army Group North, von
Leeb, sought permission to retire behind
the river Volkhov, Hitler refused him.
Von Leeb resigned his position.
>> [music]
>> Six days after von Leeb's resignation,
Timoshenko returned to the attack,
crossing the river Donets with the
intention [music] of cutting off German
troops north of the Sea of Azov.
Mhm.
By early February, outgunned and
underprepared, the Soviet counterthrust
was beginning to lose momentum.
A success early in the month, cutting
off 90,000 German troops at Demyansk,
was more than offset by the loss of the
Second Shock Army, moving north to
relieve besieged Leningrad and trapped
by a German counterattack.
By the end of March and the promise of
spring and fresh campaigning, the front
had stabilized. The winter fighting told
a story of terrible losses.
Both armies would reinforce and
re-equip.
On April the 5th, Hitler issued Führer
Directive number 41, Operation Blue, the
plan for a summer offensive to begin in
late June.
Because the Wehrmacht had survived the
winter and not been forced into a
calamitous [music]
retreat, as had Napoleon's Grande Armée,
Hitler felt that he had defied both fate
and history.
"We have," he told the Reichstag,
"mastered the destiny [music]
that broke another man 130 years ago."
Not quite.
From early May, fighting on the Eastern
Front began to crank up.
Hitler had realigned German objectives
against the advice of some of his
generals.
Turning from Moscow, he now targeted the
Donets Basin and most particularly
the Caucasian oil fields.
From the start of the war, the Royal
Navy's blockade had reduced Germany's
oil imports by 2/3. The Romanian and
Caucasian oil fields were more than
desirable. They were vital to a modern
war effort.
Von Manstein's 11th Army moved first,
attacking in the Crimea to create a
jumping-off point for the invasion of
the Caucasus.
Stalin, despite evidence to the
contrary,
clung to the belief that Germany would
renew her [music] assault on Moscow.
4 days after von Manstein began his
offensive, Stalin permitted Timoshenko
to attack towards the Dnieper, but
reserved three armies under General
Golikov in anticipation of the attack on
Moscow,
which never came.
What did come was the first phase of
Operation Blue, code named Fredericus
the First. It rolled back the Soviet
winter offensive and broke through on a
front that threatened the Caucasus to
the south and Stalingrad on the line of
advance.
Fredericus ended at the end of May.
German casualties tallied about 20,000
while Soviet losses in prisoners alone
totaled 214,000.
Hitler now flew to Poltava to consult
with his generals and approved the plan
for a summer offensive that would bring
victory in the east.
The artillery assault on Sevastopol
began on June the 2nd. The infantry was
launched on June the 8th.
The Russian garrison began to evacuate
by sea on June the 30th and the first 6
months of 1942 ended with Germany again
rampaging across the Soviet Union.
Behind their advance trailed those whose
job it was to enforce the German [music]
plan for the east.
The Germanization of the new territory
and the elimination of the subhuman, the
untermensch.
In mid-March of 1942,
almost three-quarters of those who would
die in what has come to be known as the
Holocaust were still alive.
11 months later, almost three-quarters
of those who would perish were dead.
Suddenly, we were forced into the
poorest part of town.
30,000 [music] people.
Men, women, children, babies, pregnant
women, old people, sick people, you name
it, a whole population.
They had to move into the poorest part
of town, little shacks.
But before the war, they used to live
there, maybe [music] 10, 12,000 people.
Here we were 30,000.
They finished up living 10 to a room.
Because of the hygienic conditions,
typhus set in.
So, we had a double whammy.
On January the 30th, 1942, Hitler had
made a long, rambling speech to an
enthusiastic crowd in the Berlin Sports
Palace.
He railed against England, mocked
Churchill, derided Roosevelt, praised
Japan, promised victory against
Bolshevism, and inevitably included his
most familiar motif.
"We say that the war will not end as the
Jews imagine it will," he said, "namely
with the uprooting of the Aryans, but
the result of this war will be the
complete annihilation of the Jews."
He was speaking 10 days after a
conference had commenced in a villa in
the Berlin suburb of Wannsee. It was
called the Conference of State
Secretaries, and it met to formulate a
plan for processing between 7 and 8
million units. This was the plan for the
Endlösung der Judenfrage, the final
solution of the Jewish problem.
Just over half of those who attended the
conference had doctorates. Many were
lawyers. Their orders would go out, and
almost 65% of their target would be met.
And it would be met in all of the
occupied territories on March the 27th,
the first trainload of French Jews was
sent to Poland.
It was the first of many.
Almost a million and a half of the units
whose extermination the Wannsee
Conference planned were killed not by
industrialized slaughter by gas, they
were killed by men standing a few meters
away looking down the barrel of a gun.
Those men were all given the opportunity
of declining to serve in the killing
squads, some did.
But in a regime that insisted on careful
records of everything, there is no
record of anyone ever being shot for
refusing to serve in an Einsatzgruppen,
for refusing to perform what was called
Sonderbehandlung,
special treatment.
The extraordinary determination to see
through the racist program diverted
manpower and resources away from the
battle front. It was, as Talleyrand
reportedly said of an action of
Napoleon's, worse than a crime, it was a
mistake.
The attrition of large-scale fighting
was draining Germany with its limited
capacity to resupply of men and
munitions.
Russia, on the other hand, seemed to
have a limitless capacity for
replacement, which was now being
supplemented by regular convoys of
supplies from her British and American
allies through Iran and into the
Caucasus and via the Arctic Sea.
The first Arctic convoy had left Britain
in September of 1941.
Churchill, who had given Stalin a
personal undertaking that the shuttle
would continue, insisted that the
convoys go on despite mounting losses as
they sailed into the Arctic summer and
perpetual daylight.
From the beginning of 1942, the ships
carried American supplies, lend-lease
having been extended to the USSR.
And while it is weapons that win
battles, it takes more to win a war.
American shipments [music]
to Russia included 35,000 radio
stations, 380,000
field telephones, 15,000 saws and 20,000
knives for use in amputations, and 15
million pairs of felt [music] boots made
to Soviet specifications.
Some suggest that most importantly, they
shipped quantities of Dodge and
Studebaker trucks.
All this and more was shipped on the
Arctic lifeline until, on the 27th
[music] of June, Convoy PQ 17 sailed for
Archangel.
33 merchantmen, a tanker, and more than
20 naval [music] vessels sailed.
U-boats, aircraft, and surface vessels
preyed on the convoy almost from the
start.
10 ships reached their destination.
No further Arctic convoys were
dispatched until September.
The losses to PQ 17 were part of the
reason for suspending the convoys, but
another was the pressing need to divert
shipping to the supply of Malta,
whose strategic significance was being
amplified by events in North Africa.
From its initial [music] advance on
January 21st until taking a defensive
position facing the British on the
Alamein line at the beginning of August,
[music] the Africa Corps had been
ascendant, moving through Libya into
Egypt until it threatened Alexandria and
the Suez Canal.
Once again, [music] one of Erwin
Rommel's officers remarked as they went
on the offensive, "We are Rommel-ing
ahead."
The British 1st Armoured Division had
150 tanks, but seeming to have learned
nothing from the invasion of France,
these were still dispersed like the
spread fingers of a hand.
Rommel punched with his fist.
We were back further to Derna.
With the sun
Ghanim's faster with it with so further.
Benghazi fell on January the 29th, and
the [music] offensive only paused at the
beginning of February when Rommel's fuel
stocks were dangerously low. The British
managed to reform and fortify on the
Gazala-Bir Hakeim line.
Gazala we dug in. This is
Not going to accept that this Italian
fights.
Polish, New Zealanders,
Australians,
South Africans,
Indians,
Free French.
That was our line at Gazala.
That side was the sea.
That was a soft sand. Rommel
concentrated his entire force on that
last section.
The withdrawal to Gazala denied the
Allied Desert Air Force use of the
fields in Cyrenaica, which had been
crucial to providing cover for the
convoys supplying Malta. That island's
position now became particularly
precarious.
Churchill implored his desert commander
Auchinleck to attack [music] to deny
Rommel the time he needed to re-equip
and to offer relief to Malta.
Auchinleck promised to go on the
offensive in June, but Rommel beat him
to the punch launching [music] on May
the 26th.
By then, Malta's position had not been
resolved, but it had been improved.
[music]
On May the 9th, the carriers Wasp
[music] and Eagle had managed to get
through to the island and had offloaded
60 Spitfires.
The next day, the Axis found itself
outnumbered in the sky for the first
time losing 12 aircraft for the loss of
three of the Spitfires.
By the end of May, attention was back on
North Africa. Rommel, having pushed up
to the Gazala line, opened the so-called
Battle of the Cauldron, an [music]
attempt to punch through the line, which
succeeded.
On the 5th of June, the Allies launched
their counterattack, Operation Aberdeen.
It was a failure. The British commanders
decided [music] to sit tight and wait
for Rommel to make the next move.
On the 11th, he moved. The isolated Free
French at Bir Hakeim finally fell after
a gallant fight, and Rommel, his tank
force outnumbered two to one, launched
into the gap between Knightsbridge and
El Adem.
The maneuver trapped much of the British
armor in Knightsbridge where it was
destroyed.
These German tanks, they got all
infantry on the back and they're coming
towards us and they didn't know we were
there.
And when they got close enough, of
course, I was picking them like mad
because they were chasing me.
And suddenly all the
the guns came up onto the ridge and
started knocking hell out of them.
And the infantry were running about all
over the place.
General Ritchie commanding the battle
and without referring to Auchinleck his
CNC ordered a withdrawal to the Egyptian
border leaving the vital Libyan port of
Tobruk isolated and vulnerable.
It fell to Rommel on June the 21st.
"One of the heaviest blows," Churchill
called it, "and barely beat off a
censure motion in the House of Commons."
An opinion poll found that more than
half of the British public disapproved
of their Prime Minister's handling of
the war.
And we marched out of Tobruk whilst the
Germans and Italians were bringing
British prisoners into Tobruk. And we
passed them and they [music] took not
the slightest bit of notice of us.
Of course, we got the boats and no oars,
no paddles.
And unfortunately, I got mixed up in a
firefight because the next thing I knew
was that I'm lying on the deck looking
up at two German Africa Corps types who
said to me, "For you, Tommy, the war is
over."
On June 25th, Auchinleck took over from
Ritchie.
Rommel had Mersa Matruh by the end of
June and the 8th Army [music] was back
at the Alamein line.
That's when the famous Gazala Gallop
started.
It is a every man for himself then.
If you saw a truck you didn't drive.
There was no one to give you the orders.
There was no such thing as operating.
You had to think for yourself. Nobody
was able
to take control. We were in absolute
disarray.
The threat from Rommel was felt so
urgently that the British Mediterranean
Fleet left Alexandria for Haifa.
And British HQ in Cairo began to destroy
papers preparatory to evacuating.
We lost hundreds, vehicles,
men, equipment. But just imagine.
I never thought I'd ever see Churchill
because I thought of us in Germany
first. Because he was capturing
prisoners and I was out of it.
Thanks to intercepted messages, British
intelligence was able to tell Cairo that
Rommel would resume his assault on July
the 1st, which he did.
But the British artillery was well
sighted, the Desert Air Force had
mastery of the skies, and there was
[music] a sandstorm.
By the 3rd of July, having advanced less
than 15 [music] km, Rommel ordered his
army onto the defensive. For 4 weeks
until the end of July, British and
Australian and New Zealand and South
African and Indian troops all mounted
attacks against the Axis position and
were counterattacked in turn.
But the line hardly moved.
We stopped the enemy. And I tell you,
he got trenches. Churchill couldn't dig
cuz of rocks.
I must have put in 1,000 sandbags
myself.
19 days putting putting sandbags.
Tell you this, murder.
Churchill flew to Cairo.
General [bell] Auchinleck accompanied
the premier would obviously come out
intent on seeing everything for himself
[music] and meeting as many fighting men
as possible.
Having seen everything for himself,
Churchill removed Auchinleck, appointing
Lieutenant General William Gott in his
[music] place.
The plane that Gott was traveling in was
shot down on its way to Cairo. It
crash-landed successfully thanks to the
skill of its 19-year-old pilot.
But German fighters attacked [music] the
wreck on the ground and General Gott was
killed.
His replacement was General Bernard Law
Montgomery,
Monty.
When fighting resumed in North Africa in
the second half of 1942, it would become
apparent that the odds had shifted.
The violence of global war had meanwhile
reached into quite [music] unexpected
places. The picture-perfect island of
Madagascar became a battlefield, not
because it possessed valuable resources,
but because it had the one asset that
makes real estate desirable,
location.
Its remote position, which had pre-war
seen it suggested by the Nazis as the
ideal place for the resettlement of
European Jews, was suddenly of strategic
significance. Madagascar, a French
colony garrisoned by Vichy French
troops, was a potential base from which
the Imperial Japanese Navy would be able
to threaten shipping in the Indian
Ocean.
On May the 5th, a mixed British Empire
force seized Madagascar's main port of
Diego Suarez and began an invasion that
continued until the entire island had
been suppressed in November.
Concern for the safety of merchant
shipping was also the reason for a very
different type of British action much
closer to home.
On the night of the 27th-28th of March,
an obsolete naval destroyer, HMS
Campbeltown, and a specially created
commando force attacked the naval base
at Saint-Nazaire.
Their objective, the dry dock. If they
could decommission the facility, any
Axis surface vessel in need of repair
would be forced to make the much longer
journey north.
Campbeltown was rammed into the dock
gates.
German defenses rendered useless all of
the small boats that had been the
commandos' intended means of escape.
Forced to fight, [music] the commandos
trapped had finally to surrender, after
which HMS Campbeltown, packed with
explosives on a time fuse, exploded.
The dry dock was unusable until 5 years
after [music] the end of the war.
169 men had been killed. German losses
exceeded 300.
The raid had achieved its objectives,
which encouraged thoughts of more
ambitious raids.
An amphibious assault on Dieppe was
approved and code-named Jubilee.
But Dieppe was not a jubilee.
It was nothing to celebrate.
On August the 19th, a force comprising
largely Canadian troops was delivered
with inadequate naval support
onto a shingle beach that tanks could
not cross.
Backed by esplanade walls from behind
which defenders took dreadful toll.
More than 60% [music]
of the Canadians were killed, wounded,
or captured.
The affair stands as one of the more
furiously debated controversies of the
war.
Its apologists [music]
describing the affair as reconnaissance
in depth.
Claim that though it failed as [music] a
raid,
the lessons learned about amphibious
landings
saved lives on D-Day.
Others see it differently.
They suggest that the lessons learned at
Dieppe could have been learned by
theoretical analysis of the problems of
amphibious [music] landing.
They suggest that the brave men lost
were [music] victims of wasteful,
shameful blundering.
On the other side of the Atlantic from
Dieppe, similarly flawed thinking was
responsible for equally [music] tragic
losses and what German U-boat commanders
dubbed their second happy time.
The Battle of the Atlantic never
relented. The initiative swung [music]
between ally and Axis with changes in
tactics, new ciphers, new weapons. The
second [music] happy time referred to
success against shipping on the eastern
seaboard of America. The introduction of
convoys had been resisted and the
blackout of coastal towns not
implemented until Admiral King, chief of
naval operations, saw sense. Of King,
>> [music]
>> Brigadier Dykes, secretary to the
combined Chiefs of Staff in Washington,
said he was a man of great strength of
character with a very small brain.
Losses from the start of the war until
August when the convoy system and other
defensive measures were in effect
were 609 ships and thousands of lives
lost at a cost of 22 U-boats.
The U-boats were sinking American
vessels
>> [music]
>> off the American coast because in what
may be the war's most costly decision,
Germany had declared war on the USA.
When Congress voted following the attack
on Pearl Harbor, it had been for war
with Japan.
President Roosevelt could still feel far
from sure of carrying the Congress or
the American people into war in Europe.
Such anxiety was put to rest when on
December the 10th, Adolf Hitler,
who had not up to this point formally
declared war on anyone, declared war on
the United States.
It may be that he hoped by going beyond
the terms of the Tripartite Agreement,
he would provoke his ally Japan into a
reciprocal declaration of war on the
Soviet Union.
In this, he was disappointed. Both Japan
and the Soviet Union adhered stringently
to the terms of the non-aggression pact
they had signed in April 1941.
Hitler's miscalculation was
catastrophic.
In November 1940, he had told Soviet
foreign minister [music] Molotov that
the United States would not be a
military threat until at the earliest
[music]
1970 or 1980.
When he spoke, America had an army of
100,000.
By 1945,
the United States had 14.9
million personnel in uniform. It exposed
the rank stupidity of Nazi racist
prejudice. Foreign Minister Ribbentrop
[music]
had asked, "When has a Jewified nation
like that ever produced fighters?"
Winston Churchill knew better. By
America's entry into the war, he said,
"Germany's fate was sealed. Italy's fate
was sealed. And as for the Japanese," he
added, "they would be ground to a
powder."
Hitler's gift to Roosevelt was a godsend
to Churchill. The first meeting of the
Allied leaders after America's entry
into the war, the Arcadia conference in
Washington from the end of December '41
to the middle of January '42, had
several important outcomes.
The draft charter of the United Nations
was one.
The formation of the so-called ABDA
command, American, British, Dutch,
Australian, which would cooperate
against the Japanese in the Far East,
was another.
For Churchill, the most profound outcome
was the president's decision, which,
without Hitler's declaration of war,
would have been politically impossible,
to endorse Churchill's master strategy
for the war.
Hitler must be defeated first before
attention turns to the destruction of
Japan.
>> By mid-January of 1942, Japan's
extraordinary progress across the
Asia-Pacific region must have been
giving some in the American High Command
reason to question the call, and many
did.
Japan's outrageous plan left the greater
part of its army in China, whilst a vast
and rapid conquest was launched hours
before the strike on Pearl Harbor.
The Kotabaru Field Force attacked the
east coast of Malaya 2 and 1/2 hours
before the first bomb fell on Pearl
Harbor. 3 hours after the attack on
Pearl, the Japanese attacked Hong Kong.
Soon, attacks would begin on the Dutch
East Indies, on the Philippines, south
[music] towards New Guinea, and
thrusting down the Malay Peninsula to
Singapore, more than 6,000 km from
Tokyo.
>> [music]
>> The Japanese would spread through the
Pacific, a vast but not an empty ocean.
A ring of fortified islands would make
the Co-Prosperity [music] Sphere
defensible, and these would include
islands formerly German colonies that
had been ceded to Japan at Versailles.
The Marshalls, the Carolines, and the
Marianas.
In just 6 months, the Imperial Japanese
Army and Navy would be in possession of
1/6 of the earth's surface.
In the next episode of The Price of
Empire, Japanese military forces surge
across the Asia-Pacific region,
seemingly unstoppable and unbeatable.
The middle of 1942 is the middle of the
war.
And in the second half of the year, at
Midway, at El Alamein, and in
Stalingrad, the tide begins to turn.
>> [music]